<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<blog>
    
    <entry>
    
        <title>Alumni Fair Reflection</title>
        
        <preview>The Alumni Fair was an invaluable experience that has bolstered my confidence however it has not really chanegd my post-secondary plans. It was very pleasing to hear that is room for recreation if time is managed well enough</preview>
        
        <content> The Alumni Fair was an invaluable experience that has bolstered my confidence however it has not really chanegd my post-secondary plans. It was very pleasing to hear that is room for recreation if time is managed well enough. I have generally managed my time well, so I was glad to hear that I would be able to have some free time post-secondary which, as everyone knows, is a precious resource. The Alumni Fair also eased some of my anxiety about the workload in a post-secondary environment, as most of the alumni said that it was manageable. The Alumni Fair also gave me the impression that changing one's major is an accessible feat, which is also nice to hear, because it is an option at my disposal, should I ever decide to go down that route. \n

        While there was a lot of useful insight, my plans for post-secondary schooling have not really changed because I felt that the discussion — both in the groups and when the alumni were on stage — focused more on the life of college, rather than any kind of acceptance process or recommendations for picking a college. I am still rather unsure as to what direction I want to go it, but I'm sure that I will find my way.</content>
        <date> March 30, 2016 </date>
    
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
    
        <title>Fun with Science Reflection</title>
        
        <preview>As part of the STEM Scholars program, all scholars participated in a community service project. Myself and several other members of the group decided to host a science fair for all students in the district, including middle and elementary students</preview>
        
        <content>As part of the STEM Scholars program, all scholars participated in a community service project. Myself and several other members of the group decided to host a science fair for all students in the district, including middle and elementary students. The fair was planned to be held on August 6th of 2016, but unfortunately the fair did not receive enough interest so it was canceled. \n

        The group consisted of four members including myself, and no concrete roles were assigned. I had mainly done the communicated with the administration of the district to reserve the high school cafeteria for use of the fair as well as send a district-wide message to the parents with the details of the fair. I also managed the Facebook page for the fair which did receive decent exposure to the target audience, the parents of the district, and I also communicated with the Town Crier to get coverage in the newspaper. In addition to this, I created some branding assets for the fair. \n

        The fair was a failure for several reasons. The biggest issue with the fair was lack of student interest. We had visited the middle school and spoken to several of the grades in their entirety, who expressed an interest in the fair when prompted. Perhaps the issue with this event was that it was held very close to the end of the school year and the details of the fair were not yet concrete, causing communication issues with the students. In addition to this, we were unsure if the teachers had distributed the link to sign up to the students, which may have accounted for the lack of signups. Another issue that plagued the fair was the lack of proper internal communication. The group did not communicate very well and for a long time the group had been under the misconception that the cafeteria of the high school was reserved, but it was not until only a few weeks before and the wrong venue had been advertised already. These communication issues had still not been resolved even after a meeting of the group, and unfortunately I had to pick up the slack because some of the other group members failed to recognize the severity of the lack of organization. \n

        Eventually we had voted to cancel the fair, days before it had taken place. Although the fair was a failure it did teach me important skills to hopefully organize similar events in the future. If I were to organize another science fair, my first priority would be to work out the details months and reserve a venue immediately so that all information given out to people would be immutable. I would also take action to ensure that the information had been given out properly to the students so that they at least had the ability to sign up if they wished to. And lastly I would meet more frequently with the group to ensure that there was proper communication throughout the process. \n</content>
        <date> September 4, 2016 </date>
        
        <image>assets/image/stem/fun_with_science.jpg</image>
    
    </entry>

</blog>
